Guide to the Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast Records 1883-1974
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Records
1883-1974
Oregon Historical Society Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Mss 364
Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast
1.2 cubic feet 3 document cases, 1 oversize folder
Records of an organization that worked to secure pensions for veterans of Indian wars in the Pacific Northwest. Includes organizational records, minutes of meetings, membership rosters, and correspondence of Henry H. Woodward, head of the Umpqua Camp. Also includes records and correspondence of the Sons and Daughters of Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast.
Historical Note
Founded in 1885, the Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast stated its objective as follows: "To keep alive the memories of trials of pioneer life, to encourage friendship and benevolence among those who have acted as the vanguard of civilization, to transmit a true history of the Indian wars of the North Pacific Coast, and to impress ourselves and our posterity with that true patriotism which protects our homes free from all evils both by war and peace." Individual camps were organized around Oregon and Washington, including the Umpqua Camp at Roseburg and the Multnomah Camp at Portland. The group's "Grand Encampment" was held once a year, often in Portland. In 1887 M. R. Hathaway became the Grand Adjutant. Later T. A. Wood became the Grand Commander.
One of the main goals of the organization was to secure government pensions for men who had fought in the Indian wars. The culmination of this effort came in February of 1913 when President Taft signed a bill giving the veterans a pension of $20 per month. The organization continued until circa 1941, by which time most of the original Indian war veterans had died. An associated organization, the Sons and Daughters of Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast (known as the McMillan Camp after 1941), continued in existence until 1972.
The collection contains fragmentary records of the main organization of the Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast, plus records of two subsidiary groups, the Umpqua Camp No. 6 and the Multnomah Camp No. 2. Also included are records of the Sons and Daughters of Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast, primarily the McMillan Camp. Included are minutes of meetings, financial records, correspondence, membership rosters, membership applications, printed materials and ephemera. Of particular interest is the extensive correspondence, circa 1885-1910, of the Umpqua Camp Commander Henry H. Woodward, headquartered at Roseburg, Oregon, which includes many letters from Grand Adjutant, M. R. Hathaway, and Grand Commander Thomas Alexander Wood. Subjects include organizing meetings, raising funds, and lobbying the U.S. Congress for pension benefits.
Records of the Sons and Daughters group includes membership applications providing biographical and genealogical information on members. Also included is a humorous essay by Oregon Historical Society Director Thomas Vaughan concerning the final meeting of the organization in 1974.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: Records of the Main Organization
Series B: Records of Subsidiary Groups
Series C: Records of the Sons and Daughters Group
The collection is open to the public.
Gifts of: The Estate of Georgia Smith Ringland, May 1972, Library Accession 12261; and Sons and Daughters of Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast, c/o Susan M. Hill, January 27, 1959 and Nov. 1972, Library Accessions 7840 and 12394.
Pension files compiled by the Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast are designated Mss 364-1, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Kleeman, Otto; Wood, Thomas Alexander--Correspondence; Woodward, Henry H., fl. 1886-1910
Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast; Sons and Daughters of Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast
Veterans--Oregon--Associations, institutions, etc.; Pacific Coast Indians, Wars with, 1847-1865
Military; Oregon; Pacific Northwest History; Pioneers
Minutes
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Records of the Main Organization, Series A
  - History of the organization by Otto Kleeman, circa 1942 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1890; 1898 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Records of Annual Encampments (ledger book, formerly vol. 3), 1885-1933 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Records of Annual Encampments (ledger book, formerly vol. 4), 19237-1941 (Box-folder 1/4)
    Includes joint meetings with the Sons and Daughters group.
  - Forms, legal papers, and ephemera, 1887-1924 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Includes roster of Multnomah Camp No. 2, 1890.
  - Lists of claimants for pensions, 1896-1909; undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - List of membership, 1941, Jan. 1 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Memorials to the U.S. Congress (printed), 1886; 1895 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Subscription book, 1910-1932 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Posters for annual business meetings, 1906; 1909 (Box-folder Oversize Folder)
- Records of Subsidiary Groups, Series B
  - Multnomah Camp No. 2--Constitution and by-laws (formerly vol. 1), 1888 (Box-folder 1/10)
    Includes biographies of some members.
  - Multnomah Camp No. 2--Accounts (formerly vol. 5), 1886-1894 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Dues receipts, 1885-1895 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Umpqua Camp No. 6-- Minutes (formerly vol. 2), 1885-1896 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Umpqua Camp No. 6--Minutes and roster (formerly vol. 6), 1885-1887 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Umpqua Camp No. 6--Correspondence of H. H. Woodward, 1883-1910 (Box-folder 2/5-6)
    Includes correspondence with Thomas A. Wood and M. R. Hathaway.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1927-1934; undated (Box-folder 2/7)
- Sons and Daughters of Indian War Veterans of the North Pacific Coast, Series C
  - By-laws, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Minutes of meetings (formerly vol. 7), 1908-1936 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Minutes of meetings, McMillan Camp, 1944-1959 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Minutes of meetings, McMillan Camp, 1959-1972 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Correspondence and miscellany, 1911-1973; undated (Box-folder 3/3)
    Includes humorous essay by Thomas Vaughan concerning the final meeting of the organization, 1974.
  - Accounts, 1949-1962 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Membership ledger, 1909-1938 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Membership log (formerly vol. 11), 1930-1937 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Membership dues book (formerly vol. 9), 1940-1941 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Membership applications--Yearly dues, 1938-1960 (Box-folder 3/8-9)
  - Membership applications, 1938-1967 (Box-folder 3/10)